Guide to the Mathew B. Brady and Levin Corbin Handy Photographic Studios Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Levin Corbin Handy Studio, 1849-circa 1956; Series II; (28 boxes)
  - Photographic Negatives, 817 photographic negatives, consisting of 375 glass negatives and 442 film negatives
    - Photographic Negatives: Film Negatives, Smaller than 4" X 5", (357 film negatives)
      - Unidentified locations, exterior portraits
        - Men, women, and children among rocks (Box 42, Folder 2144-2145)
        - Men, women, and children around a picnic table (Box 42, Folder 2146)
        - Men, women, and children eating watermelons (Box 42, Folder 2147)
        - Men, women, and children sitting on chairs on a porch (Box 42, Folder 2148)
        - Three men (Box 42, Folder 2149)
        - Three men and a dog in a boat (Box 42, Folder 2150)
        - Three men posed standing in front of Washington National Airport (Box 42, Folder 2151-2152)
        - Three women (Box 42, Folder 2153-2156)
        - Three women and a boy (Box 42, Folder 2157)
        - Three women and a man behind them (Box 42, Folder 2158)
        - Three women and two men (Box 42, Folder 2159)
        - Three women posed in the water (Box 42, Folder 2160)
        - Three women posed standing by an automobile (Box 42, Folder 2161)
        - Three women wearing bathing suits (Box 42, Folder 2162)
        - Three women, a man, and a boy (Box 42, Folder 2163-2165)
        - Two boys eating from bowls on the same chair (Box 42, Folder 2166)
        - Two children in a rowboat (Box 42, Folder 2167-2168)
        - Two girls and a boy (Box 42, Folder 2169)
        - Two men (Box 42, Folder 2170-2174)
        - Two men and a woman (Box 42, Folder 2175)
        - Two men and three children displaying a line of fish in the water (Box 42, Folder 2176)
        - Two men and three women (Box 42, Folder 2177)
        - Two men with two women in the background on the porch of a house (Box 42, Folder 2178)
        - Two women (Box 42, Folder 2179-2181)
        - Two women and a boy, and another man and woman in the background (Box 42, Folder 2182)
        - Two women and a boy, woman on left identified as Alice Handy Cox and the boy as Edgar Frederick Cox (Box 42, Folder 2183)
        - Two women and a man (Box 42, Folder 2184)
        - Two women and boy on a rock, woman on right identified as Alice Handy Cox (Box 42, Folder 2185)
        - Two women and boy, woman on left identified as Alice Handy Cox (Box 42, Folder 2186)
        - Two women and three men (Box 42, Folder 2187)
        - Two women and two boys (Box 42, Folder 2188-2189)
        - Two women by an automobile (Box 42, Folder 2190)
        - Two women on a powerboat (Box 42, Folder 2191)
        - Two women posed standing by a water shore (Box 42, Folder 2192)
        - Two women sitting in an automobile (Box 42, Folder 2193-2193A)
        - Two women, a man, and boy, by a picnic table (Box 42, Folder 2194)
        - Woman (Box 42, Folder 2195-2211)
        - Woman and a boy (Box 42, Folder 2212-2217)
        - Woman and a boy on snow-covered ground (Box 42, Folder 2218)
        - Woman and a man (Box 42, Folder 2219-2220)
        - Woman and boy by an automobile (Box 42, Folder 2223)
        - Woman and boy on snow-covered ground, identified as Alice Handy Cox and Edgar Frederick Cox (Box 42, Folder 2224)
        - Woman and boy posed standing in the doorway of a stone building (Box 42, Folder 2225)
        - Woman and boy, identified as Alice Handy Cox and Edgar Frederick Cox (Box 42, Folder 2226-2229)
        - Woman and child by an automobile (Box 42, Folder 2230)
        - Woman and man posed sitting (Box 42, Folder 2231)
        - Woman and man, woman identified as Maggie Claspy (Box 42, Folder 2232)
        - [Empty envelope] (Box 42, Folder 2233)
        - Woman and two children in an automobile (Box 42, Folder 2234)
        - Woman holding an infant (Box 42, Folder 2235)
        - Woman in an automobile (Box 42, Folder 2236)
        - Woman posed mounted on a horse (Box 42, Folder 2237)
        - Woman posed sitting in a chair (Box 42, Folder 2238)
        - Woman posed standing (Box 42, Folder 2239)
        - Woman with flowers (Box 42, Folder 2240)
        - Woman, identified as Alice Handy Cox (Box 42, Folder 2241)
      - Unidentified location, interior portraits
        - Alice Handy Cox and Edgar Frederick Cox (Box 42, Folder 2242-2245)
        - Eastern Airlines office, man (Box 42, Folder 2246)
        - Eastern Airlines office, two men (Box 42, Folder 2247-2248)
        - Eastern Airlines office, woman (Box 42, Folder 2249)
        - Edgar Cox and Edgar Frederick Cox (Box 42, Folder 2250)
        - Elderly woman holding an infant (Box 42, Folder 2251)
        - Girl (Box 42, Folder 2252)
        - Infant (Box 42, Folder 2253)
        - Man (Box 42, Folder 2254-2261)
        - Man and boy sitting by a fireplace (Box 42, Folder 2262)
        - Man posed sitting at a piano (Box 42, Folder 2263)
        - Mrs. John Bright Handy and Ashley Handy (Box 42, Folder 2264)
        - Seven boys around a table (Box 42, Folder 2265)
        - Three men (Box 42, Folder 2266)
        - Three men posed by a cake (Box 42, Folder 2267)
        - Three women (Box 42, Folder 2268)
        - Three women and a man (Box 42, Folder 2269)
        - Two women (Box 42, Folder 2270)
        - Woman (Box 42, Folder 2271-2272)
        - Woman, 1954 Nov (Box 42, Folder 2273)
        - Woman at a desk, 1955 Mar (Box 42, Folder 2274)
        - Woman holding an infant (Box 42, Folder 2275)
        - Woman in a bed (Box 42, Folder 2276-2277)
        - Woman in a bed and a woman posed sitting (Box 42, Folder 2278)
        - Woman in an automobile (Box 42, Folder 2279-2280)
        - Woman posed sitting at a piano (Box 42, Folder 2281)
      - Studio portraits, copy photographs
        - Diamond, Ida (Box 42, Folder 2282)
        - Grier, Judge (Box 42, Folder 2283)
        - Handy, Levin C. (Box 42, Folder 2284)
        - Madison, Dolly (Box 42, Folder 2285-2286)
          From a daguerreotype
        - Infant (Box 42, Folder 2287-2290)
        - Three boys and two women (Box 42, Folder 2291-2292)
        - Woman (Box 42, Folder 2293-2296)
    - Photographic Film Negatives, Stereographs, (34 film negatives)
      Stereographic film negatives created by the studio of Levin C. Handy and members of the Handy family that document locations in Virginia and Washington, D.C., and the activities and individuals in the extended Handy family. Most of the individuals are unidentified in the images.
      - District of Columbia, Washington. Washington Monument. From Arlington National Cemetery, Virginia, 1924 Aug 16 (Box 43, Folder 2297)
      - Virginia, Arlington National Cemetery
        - Gravesite of Georges St. John, 1924 Aug 16 (Box 43, Folder 2298)
        - Gravesites, 1924 Aug 16 (Box 43, Folder 2299)
        - Tomb of the Unknown Soldier with Mr. Robert, Alice Handy Cox, and Mrs. Lloyd, 1924 Aug 16 (Box 43, Folder 2300)
      - Unidentified locations
        - Across water to trees on land (Box 43, Folder 2301)
        - Automobile with a man, woman, and child inside it on a street (Box 43, Folder 2302)
        - Automobiles on a street in front of buildings (Box 43, Folder 2303)
        - Building with automobiles on a wet road (Box 43, Folder 2304)
        - Children running toward the camera (Box 43, Folder 2305)
        - Demolished building (Box 43, Folder 2306-2307)
        - Four men in a motorboat (Box 43, Folder 2308-2309)
        - From above of a bridge with children, women, and men on it (Box 43, Folder 2310)
        - House on shore from the water (Box 43, Folder 2311-2312)
        - Man on a boat by a pier (Box 43, Folder 2313)
        - Man on a pier and two men in a boat (Box 43, Folder 2314)
        - Men, women, and children in water (Box 43, Folder 2315)
        - Men, women, and children in water by a pier (Box 43, Folder 2316)
        - Motor boat on the water (Box 43, Folder 2317)
        - People standing outside a wooden house in the distance (Box 43, Folder 2318)
        - Street scene from the front yard of a house (Box 43, Folder 2319)
        - Two children riding a horse (Box 43, Folder 2320)
        - Woman riding a horse, accompanied by a man and a boy (Box 43, Folder 2321)
        - Wooden building by a water shore (Box 43, Folder 2322)
        - Wooden building identified as a dining room (Box 43, Folder 2323)
      - Unidentified locations, exterior portraits
        - Alice Handy Cox holding Edgar Frederick Cox, 1926 Nov 21 (Box 43, Folder 2324)
        - Handy family (Box 43, Folder 2325-2327)
        - Handy family posed standing by two automobiles (Box 43, Folder 2328-2330)
    - Photographic Film Negatives, 5" X 7", (22 film negatives)
      Film negatives created by the studio of Levin C. Handy that document the Handy family at the studio in Washington, D.C., and copy photographs of Gardner's Photographic Sketchbook of the Civil War, by Alexander Gardner.
      Arranged alphabetically by identified location, unidentified locations, studio portraits, and then copy photography.
      - District of Columbia, Washington. Handy family at the Levin C. Handy Studio (Box 43, Folder 2331-2332)
      - Unidentified locations
        - Lee Camp Hall and veterans starting on Confederate Memorial Day, 1906 (Box 43, Folder 2333-2334)
        - Exterior portrait of two men posed standing (Box 43, Folder 2335)
      - Studio portrait of a woman (Box 43, Folder 2336)
      - Copy Photographs from Gardner's Photographic Sketchbook of the Civil War, by Alexander Gardner
        - Maryland, Sharpsburg. James Dunker Church (Box 43, Folder 2337)
        - Pennsylvania, Gettysburg
          - H. Trossell residence (Box 43, Folder 2338)
          - Round Top. Breastworks (Box 43, Folder 2339)
          - Slaughter Pen (Box 43, Folder 2340)
        - Virginia
          - Aquia Creek. Office of the Provost Marshall (Box 43, Folder 2341)
          - Belle Plain. Camp of Confederate prisoners (Box 43, Folder 2342)
          - Centreville. Quaker guns (Box 43, Folder 2343)
          - Centreville. Stone Church (Box 43, Folder 2344)
          - Chickahominy River. Military bridge (Box 43, Folder 2345)
          - Fredericksburg. 5th United States Artillery, Battery D, in Action (Box 43, Folder 2346)
          - Rappahannock River. Pontoon bridge (Box 43, Folder 2347)
          - Yorktown. Moore House (Box 43, Folder 2348)
          - Yorktown, vicinity. Battery No. 1 (Box 43, Folder 2349)
      - Copy photographs
        - Studio portrait of four women, including Lizzie Riley, a teacher at the old Jefferson School, from a tintype (Box 43, Folder 2350)
        - Studio portrait of Abraham Lincoln (Box 43, Folder 2351)
          Positive transparency
        - Painting of a woman wearing a kimono (Box 43, Folder 2352)
          Autochrome
        - Verso of photographic print of Abraham Lincoln with Major General George Brinton McClellan which was presented by Lincoln to Captain D. V. Dickson, 1862 Oct 27 (Box 43, Folder 2353)
        - Engraving. Election day in the army of the Shenandoah (Box 43, Folder 2354)
    - Photographic Film Negatives, 3" X 9", (22 film negatives)
      Film negatives created by the studio of Levin C. Handy and members of the Handy family that document activities and individuals in the extended Handy family. Many of the individuals in the images are unidentified.
      - Unidentified locations
        - Building near a shore (Box 44, Folder 2355)
        - Canoes on a water shore (Box 44, Folder 2356)
        - Canoes on a water shore and on the water (Box 44, Folder 2357)
        - Fields and buildings in the distance (Box 44, Folder 2358)
        - Forest (Box 44, Folder 2359-2365)
        - Forest and a water shore (Box 44, Folder 2366)
        - Man and woman in a row boat on water (Box 44, Folder 2367)
        - Men and women sitting at tables on a porch and yard (Box 44, Folder 2368)
        - River with rocky shores (Box 44, Folder 2369-2371)
        - Road beside a canal (Box 44, Folder 2372)
        - Sailboats on water (Box 44, Folder 2373-2374)
        - Shoreline with a pier (Box 44, Folder 2375)
        - Woman posed standing, possible Mary Handy Evans (Box 44, Folder 2376)
    - Photographic Film Negatives, 8" X 10", (7 film negatives)
      Film negatives that document locations in Virginia and Washington, D.C., and portrait of Handy family members.
      Arranged alphabetically by location, followed by studio portraits.
      - District of Columbia. Washington.
        - 5th Baptist Church. Baraca Class, 1929 May (Box 44, Folder 2377-2378)
        - Levin C. Handy Studio, interior, including Alice Handy Cox and Edgar Cox (Box 44, Folder 2379)
      - Virginia, Mount Vernon. Interior of the family dining room (Box 44, Folder 2380)
      - Unidentified location, exterior portrait of the Levin C. Handy family that shows four generations (Box 44, Folder 2381-2382)
      - Studio portrait of Levin Corbin Handy (Box 44, Folder 2383)
    - Oversize Photographic Glass Negatives, (2 glass negatives)
      Oversize glass negatives created by the studio of Levin C. Handy.
      - District of Columbia. Washington. 17th Street NW and Constitution Avenue NW, circa 1895 (Box 45, Folder 2384)
        Accompanied by a photographic print
      - Unidentified location, exterior portrait of Robert Edward Lee (Box 45, Folder 2385)
  - Papers
    Financial records documenting the location and operations of the Levin Corbin Handy Studio in Washington, D.C., as well as notes on historical subjects.
    - Negative ledgers
      Fragments of studio negative ledgers
      - Le-Wh, no date (Box 46, Folder 2386)
      - 2106-2118, no date (Box 46, Folder 2387)
    - Financial Records
      - Receipt to Levin Corbin Handy from W. O. Berry, 1888 Jan 14 (Box 46, Folder 2388)
      - Property taxes, 494 Maryland Avenue SW, Washington, District of Columbia, 1949-1952 (Box 46, Folder 2389)
      - Ledger, 1950 (Box 46, Folder 2390)
      - Outgoing invoices, 1954 (Box 46, Folder 2391)
      - Statement letterhead, L. C. Handy Studios, no date (Box 46, Folder 2392)
    - Property deeds for 494 Maryland Avenue SW, Washington, District of Columbia, 1849 Oct 4 -1949 Oct 13 (Box 46, Folder 2393)
    - Other
      - Library card to the Library of Congress, 1944 Mar 8 (Box 46, Folder 2394)
      - Calendar, 1947 Jan, 1951 Feb-Aug (Box 46, Folder 2395)
      - Parking enclosure permit, 1948 (Box 46, Folder 2396)
      - Letter of support for James David Horan, circa 1956 (Box 46, Folder 2397)
      - Notes
        Arranged alphabetically by the surname of the subject and corporate name of the subject.
        - Barnum's American Museum (Box 46, Folder 2398)
        - Boats (Box 46, Folder 2399)
        - Clymer, George (Box 46, Folder 2400)
        - Dickinson, Anna Elizabeth (Box 46, Folder 2401)
        - Eaton, Margaret O'Neill (Box 46, Folder 2402)
        - Emancipation Memorial designed by Thomas Ball (Box 46, Folder 2403)
        - Halleck, Fitz-Greene (Box 46, Folder 2404)
        - Hayes, Isaac Israel (Box 46, Folder 2405)
        - Healy, George Peter Alexander (Box 46, Folder 2406)
        - Lincoln, Abraham (Box 46, Folder 2407)
          Newspaper clippings
        - Postage stamp honoring Franklin Delano Roosevelt (Box 46, Folder 2408)
        - Postage stamp honoring the Philippines, 1944 (Box 46, Folder 2409)
        - Pleasonton, Alfred (Box 46, Folder 2410)
        - Sedgwick, Theodore (Box 46, Folder 2411)
        - Sprague, Katherine Jane Chase (Box 46, Folder 2412)
        - Thomas, Philip Francis (Box 46, Folder 2413)
        - Townsend, Edward Davis (Box 46, Folder 2414)
        - Various lantern slides (Box 46, Folder 2415)
        - World War I (Box 46, Folder 2416)
- Family Papers and Photographs, 1843-1957; Series III; 5 boxes (including 1 oversize box)
  Family papers and photographs of the extended Handy family include financial records and correspondence, as well as studio portraits and informal portraits of family members.
  Subseries arranged with papers followed by photographic materials and then oversize photographic materials.
  - Papers
    Finacial records, primarily related to family property and correspondence between family members.
    Arranged chronologically within each heading.
    - Financial papers
      - Apprentice contract of William Henry Bright to learn bricklaying from Thomas Lewis, 1843 (Box 47, Folder 2417)
      - Notebook fragment of George M. Kendall, 1857 Dec 3, 1858 Feb 1 (Box 47, Folder 2418)
        Discussion of the financial affairs of his deceased daughter, Caroline W. Kendall Price
      - Probate record for the estate of Ira Marks to Robert Wilson Livingston and Byron Pond, 1865 Nov 13 (Box 47, Folder 2419)
      - Rent receipt to Samuel S. Handy from A. Hyde, acting for William Wilson Corcoran, 1866 Apr 21 (Box 47, Folder 2420)
      - Will of Elizabeth Bright Kendall, 1889 Jul 2 (Box 47, Folder 2421)
      - Deed quit claims to the estate of Elizabeth Bright Kendall to Mary Ann Handy by John Fulmer Bright and William Henry Bright, 1889 Jul-Sep (Box 47, Folder 2422)
      - Payment Coupons. Block 14, Lot 3, in Riverside Park, Fairfax County, Virginia, 1894 (Box 47, Folder 2423)
      - Tax Bill. Block 14, Lot 3, in Riverside Park, Fairfax County, Virginia, 1944 (Box 47, Folder 2424)
      - Income tax, Mary Handy Evans, 1947 (Box 47, Folder 2425)
      - Incoming invoice for walnut shelves sold to the Abraham Lincoln home, 1953 Sep (Box 47, Folder 2426)
    - Deeds
      - Burial plots in Washington Cemetery, 1853 Jan 25, 1857 Aug 21 (Box 47, Folder 2427)
      - Block 14, Lot 3, in Riverside Park, Fairfax County, Virginia, 1895, 1897 (Box 47, Folder 2428)
      - Shellfield, Westmoreland County, Virginia, 1910 Oct 20 (Box 47, Folder 2429)
    - Other
      - Guardian certificate of Mary A. Handy, 1875 Oct 12 (Box 47, Folder 2430)
      - Commencement program from Washington Normal School, 1876 Jun 9 (Box 47, Folder 2431)
      - Manuscript biography of Mathew B. Brady, circa 1900 (Box 47, Folder 2432)
      - Address book, probably owned by Alice Handy Cox, circa 1920-1922 (Box 47, Folder 2433)
      - Marriage announcement of Alice Margaret Handy and Edgar Cunningham Cox, 1921 Nov 18 (Box 47, Folder 2434)
      - Birth announcement of Edgar Frederick Cox, 1926 Jul 9 (Box 47, Folder 2435)
      - Cradle Roll promotion certificate of Edgar Frederick Cox, 1930 Sep 28 (Box 47, Folder 2436)
      - Membership card of Jefferson Junior High School Parent-Teacher Association of Alice Handy Cox, 1939 Sep (Box 47, Folder 2437)
      - Honor diploma from Jefferson Junior High School of Edgar Frederick Cox, 1939 Feb 3 (Box 47, Folder 2438)
      - Newspaper clipping, "Jefferson Junior High Presents Diplomas to 100 in Class," including Edgar Frederick Cox, circa 1939 (Box 47, Folder 2439)
      - Newspaper clippings, "Congress Library Gets Photo Gems" and "Library of Congress Get Handy Studio Photo Collection", 1954 (Box 47, Folder 2440)
      - Information Bulletin, Library of Congress, 1954 Oct 11 (Box 47, Folder 2441)
      - Program from the funeral of Blanche Cox Bittner, 1955 Mar 31 (Box 47, Folder 2442)
      - Newspaper clipping, obituary of Mary Handy Evans, 1957 (Box 47, Folder 2443)
      - Newspaper clipping, "Social Side of Politiking... ,"Northern Virginia Sun, 1958 Oct 31 (Box 47, Folder 2444)
        Halftone of Alice Handy Cox and Edgar Cox with Joel T. Broyhill
      - Typescript, "Mathew Brady, Wet plate historian," by George Kuster and Edgar Frederick Cox, 1959 (Box 47, Folder 2445)
      - Newspaper clipping, "Family Heirloom", circa 1960 (Box 47, Folder 2446)
        Halftone portrait of Edgar Frederick Cox
      - Newspaper clipping, obituary of Alice Handy Cox, 1964 (Box 47, Folder 2447)
      - Genealogical notes, Robert Jenkins Henry Handy and William Robert Handy, no date (Box 47, Folder 2448)
  - Correspondence
    - Bright and Handy family, 1844-1845, 1850-1852, 1857, 1874-1875, 1877, 1879, 1890, 1894, 1904, 1951, 1954-1955, 1957, no date; (33 items) (Box 47, Folder 2449-2460)
      Much of the early correspondence under this heading deals with family financial matters. This includes a letter of indenture of William Henry Bright (the brother of Mary Ann Bright Handy and uncle of Levin Corbin Handy), 1843.
      Letters from Robert Handy, serving aboard the United States Revenue Cutters Morris and Howard, to his brother Samuel S. Handy in 1850 include mentions of Brady and his wife living on Staten Island, New York, and the aftermath of the sinking of the bark, Elizabeth, on July 19, 1850.
      Letters from Levin Corbin Handy to his then future wife, Emma Sussanna Gessford, include one asking her to attend a prayer meeting in 1874, as well as love poems he wrote to her in 1875 and undated. They were married in 1879.
      Single letters of interest to researchers and philographers include an autograph letter signed from Senator Jefferson Davis to Secretary of War John Buchanan Floyd in 1857, and an undated autographed letter signed by Robert Lincoln to Levin Corbin Handy.
    - Gessford family, 1870, 1879, 1911, 1924, 1939, no date; (14 items) (Box 47, Folder 2461-2466)
      This heading includes letters between Joseph Gessford and Emma Sussanna Gessford document his service aboard the USS Wyoming, 1879.
    - Johnson family, 1857, 1861-1862, 1869, 1932, no date; (10 items) (Box 47, Folder 2467-2468)
      Primarily Letters from John W. Johnston, a Second Lieutenant in the 39th Regiment, Ohio Infantry, to his wife, Elizabeth Johnston, and his sister in Medina, Ohio, document his service in the American Civil War during 1862.
    - Kendall family, 1842, 1854, 1857-1859, 1861-1862, 1864-1869, 1871-1875, 1887, no date; (33 items) (Box 47, Folder 2469-2474)
      The correspondence especially documents the family of George M. Kendall (1787-1874), the husband of Elizabeth Bright Kendall (1802-1889), the grandmother of Levin Corbin Handy.
    - William Plume Moran, 1843, 1848, 1862; (3 items) (Box 47, Folder 2475)
      Letters of appointment for William Plume Moran (1810-1897), one of the original clerks for the United States Navy, who served in that role for fifty-three years. Autograph letters signed by a United States Secretary of the Navy, including David Henshaw in 1843, John Young Mason in 1848, and Gideon Welles in 1862.
    - Steward family, 1865-1866, 1885, no date; (6 items) (Box 47, Folder 2476)
      Letters from Matilda Steward to her son, Reverend Lanson Steward (born 1824), and his wife, Asby Jane Steward, and an envelope addressed to their son Thomas G. Steward, a chief clerk in the United States Patent Office.
  - Family Photographs, (133 photographic prints)
    Photographic prints depicting members of the extended Handy family include studio portraits and informal portraits of the children and grandchildren of Levin Corbin Handy. Many of the studio portraits were created by the studios of Mathew B. Brady and Levin Corbin Handy.
    Studio portraits are arranged by date followed by locations in Washington, D.C., Pennsylvania, Virginia, and unidentified locations arranged alphabetically by geographic location and then chronologically. Unidentified locations and unidentified individuals are grouped at the end by subject matter.
    - Studio portraits
      - Levin Corbin Handy, circa 1867 (Box 48, Folder 2477)
      - George Handy, circa 1870 (Box 48, Folder 2478)
      - John Bright Handy, circa 1872 (Box 48, Folder 2479)
      - John Bright Handy on a tricycle, circa 1872 (Box 48, Folder 2480)
      - Emma Sussanna Gessford Handy, circa 1883 (Box 48, Folder 2481)